Guide to the Donald M. Goldstein Collection, 1886-2005 UA.90.F78
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Photographs, XIII.
  - World War II, 2.
    - Nuts! The Battle of the Bulge: The Story and the Photographs
      - Published Images, 1940s (Box Photo 8, Folder 15-23)
        - The infantryman from the previous photo advances toward Poteau from the same position but now in the correct direction., 202.
        - Looking south toward Poteau, the orientation of the U.S. armored car's turret (right) documents the likely direction of the initial attack that precipitated the American panic., 203.
          The marking on the M8 at right, "1A 18C," indicated that the armored car belonged to the 18th Cavalry Reconnaissance Squadron, which was assigned to the First Army. Note the vehicle's tires are equipped with snow chains.
        - View looking back up the road toward Recht., 204.
        - A Luftwaffe Unteroffizier armed with a captured M1 carbine advances south along the road embankment., 205.
        - Recruited as actors, SS infantrymen press to the north, "advancing" the wrong way down the road toward Recht instead of Poteau., 206.
          Photo number: 4-70
        - A handsome, heavily armed Grenadier tousled hair sticking out from under his helmet, pauses for the camera., 207.
          Photo number: 4-71
        - Reset and try again., 208.
          The soldiers back up for another staged advance toward Recht.
          Photo number: 4-72
        - Enough acting -- it's time for a smoke break!, 209.
        - More cigarettes for the men of the SS-Panzergrenadier-Regiment 1., 210.
          Photo number: 4-74
        - SS troops savor the fruits of victory on the road to Poteau. (left to right) SS men 2,1,4,3, and 5., 211.
          Photo number: 4-75
        - Their break over, the soldiers begin to advance, this time, at least, in the right direction., 212.
          Photo number: 4-76
        - At the photographer's behest, three Grenadiere launch an impressive if very much staged, attack to the north., 213.
          Photo number: 4-77
        - SS man 3 gets on last close-up for the home front and one last opportunity to loot American treasure, yielding a tin of rations (as prized as American cigarettes) from an armored car., 214.
          Photo number: 4-78
        - SS men 2, 1, and 3 accompany the photographer back to his vehicle, "advancing" as they go., 215.
          Photo number: 4-79
        - SS men 2 and 1 continue the advance against the backdrop of burning American vehicles., 216.
          Photo number: 4-80
        - Troops move north at the scene of the skirmish depicted in photos 4-54 and 4-55., 217.
          Photo number: 4-81
        - Two officers, one of whom is possibly the commander of the company currently in the area, pass the photographer., 218.
          Photo number: 4-82
        - The troops stage one last advance to the south while exiting from the scene., 219.
          Photo number: 4-83
        - A Jagdpanzer IV/70 bypasses the American logjam ahead by moving off onto the south side of the road., 220.
          Photo number: 4-84
        - Two self-propelled guns are moved into firing position., 221.
          Photo number: 4-85
        - Obersturmbannführer Otto Skorzeny, 150. Panzer-Brigade and leader of Operation Greif, shown here as a Hauptsturmführer., 222.
          This photo is one of several portraits of Skorzeny by Hitler's photographer, Heinrich Hoffmann. Although it has been published several times, this is the first instance where it has been used unretouched, showing Skorzeny's original rank. It was common practice for German war heroes to be "promoted" to their current rank in official photography. Note the prominent Schmisse, or dueling scar, on Skorzeny's left check.
        - A Sturmgeschütz from Hauptmann Scheff's Kampfgruppe Y that the Americans found abandoned at Geromont., 223.
          Note the white star painted on the sides and front. The 291st Combat Engineers removed a bobby trap from the vehicle on 15 January 1945.
        - After the explosion of an incendiary grenade that Skorzeny's retreating commandos had planted, a booby-trapped SdKfz 250 light half-track from the 150. Panzer-Brigade burns in Regne, Belgium., 224.
          As with the brigade's other vehicles, this one was painted olive drab and adorned with the obligatory white star.
        - An American military policeman (MP) checks the papers of a Belgian civilian near Bastogne on 21 December., 225.
        - A German soldier, partially clad in American clothing, lies dead in Hotton, Belgium., 226.
          The hapless man's dog tags have been pulled out from his tunic, presumably as evidence of his misdeeds.
        - Found guilty of espionage, Greif commandos (left to right) Wilhelm Schmidt, Günter Billing, and Manfried Pernass await their execution on 23 December., 227.
          MPs secure the trio to shooting posts erected near the wall of the building behind. Schmidt cannot look at the firing squad. The bespectacled Billing stares unblinking ahead. Pernass, not net tied to the post, looks to his leader, perhaps for inspiration of encouragement.
        - As MPs tie up Pernass, pulling his hands behind him, the convicted spy continues to look expectantly toward Billing., 228.
        - With Pernass blindfolded and secured to the shooting post, Capt. Joseph Eiser, medical officer of the 633d Clearing Station, affixes a target for the firing squad (a four-inch white circle pinned over the heart)., 229.
          A grim-faced MP stands close by. Note that are no bullet holes in the wall behind Pernass.
        - Started Signal Corps photographer Cpl. Edward A. Norbuth flinches, blurring the photographic image, as the volley from the firing squad crashes into the three prisoners and the wall behind. Four riflemen were assigned to each convicted spy., 230.
        - Gefreiter Wilhelm Schmidt pays the price of a failed mission., 231.
        - Oberst Freiherr Friedrich-August von der Heydte, shown here as a major in 1943., 232.
          A veteran parachutist and a certified German hero, von der Heydte commanded I./Fallschirmjäger-Regiment 3 during the legendary, if ill-fated, airborne assault on Crete.
        - A Junkers Ju-52 in winter camouflage wrecked when it attempted to land near Asselborn in northern Luxembourg., 233.
          Although not associated directly with Stösser, this aircraft was from one of the transport groups supporting the operation. This particular aircraft and another have often been erroneously attributed to Kampfgruppe von der Heydte, when, actually, both aircraft landed in an attempt to service a German field hospital near Asselborn.
        - An American patrol from Company F, 3d Battalion, 1st Infantry Regiment, probes the Belgian woodlands in search of German paratroopers on 18 December 1944., 234.
        - Men of the 3d Battalion, 18th Infantry Regiment, bide their time near Sourbrodt, Belgium, and wait for their comrades to flush Fallschirmjäger from the woods nearby on 19 December., 235.
        - Near Sourbrodt, Pvt. Harry N. Newton of Detroit, Michigan, examines supply containers dropped by the Luftwaffe for Operation Stösser paratroopers., 236.
        - American soldiers hold up German parachutes near Sourbrodt on 19 December, mute testimony to Operation Stösser., 237.
          Silk parachute material accompanied at least one Ardennes veteran back to the States. Capt. Arthur D. Wenger, chaplain in the 76th Division and father to one of the authors, used the silk to make pajamas. Unfortunately, the dye in the silk had no more staying power than von der Heydte's paratroopers; the pajamas ruined a set of bedsheets the first night Wenger wore them.
        - Receiving medical aid from Capt. Albert J. Haft and Lt. Col. John R. Woodruff, Oberst von der Heydte lies on a stretcher after he surrender to 99th Infantry Division troops., 238.
        - Map -- Peiper's Fateful "Detour" to Ligneuville, 239.
        - This view shows the U.S. convoy's final approach to the Baugnez crossroads, moving up the hill east from Malmédy., 240.
          Abandoned vehicles from Battery B, 285th Field Artillery Observation Battalion, still litter the side of the road.
        - View at Baugnez looking due west down the roads that fork (left) to Hedomont and (right) down the hill to Geromont and Malmédy., 241.
          The lead vehicle in the U.S. convoy was just about to make a right turn out of the photo at left toward Ligneuville and St. Vith. The truck at right, driven by Sgt. Alan M. Lucas, was actually the second vehicle in the convoy behind Lieutenant Lary's jeep. Note the house at left center, also visible in the previous photo. The ambulance at far right was driven by Pvt. Roy B. Anderson.
        - This view greeted the vehicles of Kampfgruppe Peiper as they approached Baugnez perhaps one hundred yards from the crossroads., 242.
          A shed belonging to Henri LeJoly lies on Highway N23 (the road to Ligneuville) at left. The U.S. column was just behind the line of trees at right.
        - Commander of I./SS-Panzer-Regiment 1, Sturmbannführer Werner Pötschke, shown earlier in his career as a Hauptsturmführer., 243.
          Perhaps a convenient scapegoat, Pötschke was killed in Hungary during March 1945 and thus could tell no tales or provide any rebuttal regarding the massacre.
        - The killing field., 244.
          The Bodarwé café and the U.S. convoy lie some distance behind the photographer. Highway N23, Kampfgruppe Peiper's exit route from the scene, runs toward Ligneuville between the rows of trees at left. Also visible at left is the shed of Henri Lejoly, a Belgian witness to the massacre. National Archives 111-SC-226664, 111-SC-22663, 111-SC-226508, 111-SC-226507
          Page number: 94-95
        - The burned-out ruins of Madame Adèle Bodarwé's house and café seen from the east., 245.
          Peiper's Kampfgruppe would have advanced straight toward the café in the distance behind the trees at center.
        - Henri Lejoly, civilian witness to the massacre, played a far from heroic role., 246.
          In the Bodarwé café at the time, he waved a welcome to the Germans and a little later pointed out the hiding place of some Americans. Even so, the Germans prepared to kill him because he had witnessed the massacre, but after a time let him go. National Archives 111-SC-226667
        - View from the east window of the house in photos 5-19 and 5-20, with the Bodarwé café at left and the corner of the massacre site at right., 247.
        - Highway N23, the road by which Kampfgruppe Peiper continued its advance to Ligneuville., 248.
          Note the N23 signpost at left and the shattered branches of the trees, perhaps damaged by German shellfire.
        - Men from Company C, 291st Combat Engineers, pose at Baugnez for a group photograph on 16 January 1945., 249.
        - Black soldiers from the 3200th Quartermaster Service Company, led by 2d Lt. F.J. Fraser (second row, far right) National Archives 111-SC-226884, 250.
        - An engineer walks past the head of the U.S. convoy toward the massacre field, which is just out of the photograph at left., 251.
          Jeeps head down the road to Hedomont, likely carrying more engineers. The "1A-285FOB B-2" marking on the GMC two-and-half-ton truck denotes second vehicle of Battery B, 285th Field Artillery Observation Battalion, assigned to the First Army. A Sherman tank stands next to the house in the background.
        - Using mine detectors, engineers work to locate the slain American soldiers., 252.
          This scene is viewed looking south from the road to Hedomont.
        - After sweeping away the snow, an engineer uncovers the corpse of an American Soldier., 253.
        - The grisly task of locating the American bodies continues, with the second and third bodies uncovered., 254.
        - Looking northeast toward Bodarwé's café, the photographer snaps the main group of Americans massacred at Baugnez., 255.
          Page number: 100-101
        - Two American bodies lie approximately one hundred yards from the massacre site., 256.
          The view is along south side of the road to Hedomont, looking west toward the crossroads.
        - Two black soldiers carry a victim to a waiting transport vehicle., 257.
          Private Anderson's ambulance is at left. National Archives 111-SC-226653
        - An army in retreat., 258.
          Vehicles belonging to the 99th Infantry Division withdraw to the west through the town of Wirtzfeld during 17 December 1944. Vehicles markings indicate that the truck is from the 372d Field Artillery Battalion, the 99th Infantry's heavy 155mm battalion. An M10 tank destroyer covers the withdrawal.
        - Likely from Kampfgruppe Peiper, A PzKpfw IV lies turret upended, put out of action by a tank destroyer in Wirtzfeld -- one hopes by the M10 in photo 5-37!, 259.
        - American infantry of Company G, 23d Regiment, 2d Infantry Division, dig in along an embankment on 17 December., 260.
        - Men of the 26th Regiment, 1st Infantry Division, move up to meet the German thrusts threatening the town of Büllingen on 17 December., 261.
        - The 26th Infantry Regiment's 1st Battalion advances to repel German attacks near Butgenbach during 17 December., 262.
          Note the destroyed railroad bridge in the background and the sign at left that cautions drivers about craters in the road.
        - Two Panthers of I./SS-Panzer-Regiment 12 in Krinkelt were eliminated by U.S. bazooka teams on 17 December., 263.
          Note that the side armor plating has been blown loose.
        - A Hitlerjugend crewman of Panther "126" surrenders to the Americans south of Krinkelt on 17 December., 264.
        - On 19 December the remains of a gasoline dumps that the Americans set on fire as a roadblock north of Stavelot., 265.
        - Troops of the 325th Gilder Infantry, 82d Airborne Division, move up the road near Werbomont, Belgium, on 20 December in heavy fog., 266.
        - M36 tank destroyers plunge through the gloom near Werbomont in support of the 82d Airborne Division., 267.
        - On 21 December, M10 crewman from the 823d Tank Destroyer Battalion of the 30th Division pose beside their vehicle in Stavelot, Belgium, for Signal Corps photographer V.C. Calvano., 268.
          The photo commemorates their destruction of four tanks belonging to Kampfgruppe Peiper.
        - Stavelot, 21 December., 269.
          A dead SS Leibstandarte infantryman serves as a reminder of Kampfgruppe Knittel's drive through the town on 18 December. The American reoccupied the town three days later.
        - An army convoy stops to rest in the snowscape of the Ardennes during 22 December., 270.
        - Snow covered St. Vith during the American effort to retake the town on 24 January., 271.
          Allied bombing while the town was in German hands resulted in the moonlike landscape seen here. Few buildings were left intact. National Archives 111-SC-265513
        - At XVIII Corps headquarters in Harzé, Belgium, Lieutenant General Hodges pins a Silver Star on Brig. Gen. Robert W. Hasbrouck for gallantry in action during the defense of St. Vith. 111-SC-279922, 272.
        - Maj. Gen. William H. Morris (center), commanding general, 10th Armored Division., 273.
        - Guns of the 969th Field Artillery Battalion dig in to support the 101st Airborne Division., 274.
          Here men work to unload 155mm howitzer shell cases from the ammunition truck at left.
        - 110th Infantry Regiment "orphans" from Maj. Gen. Norman Cota's 28th Infantry Division share worried expressions in Bastogne on 19 December., 275.
          The soldier at left is armed with grenades and an M1 carbine. A broadside addressed to Bastogne's inhabitants is attached to the bulletin board behind the soldiers.
        - Troops of the 506th Parachute Infantry, 101st Airborne Division, move out from Bastogne., 276.
        - Heavy artillery evacuates Bastogne during 20 December., 277.
        - Men of Company B, 630th Tank Destroyer Battalion (sans M36s), armed only with rifles, dig in at their roadblock near Wiltz., 278.
        - Major Rolf Kunkel, Kampfgruppe leader, 26. Volksgrenadier-Division, shown here earlier in the war as a young Leutnant., 279.
          Kunkel commanded his division's Aufklärungs-Abteilung 26.
        - Brig. Gen. Anthony C. McAuliffe, acting commander of the 101st Airborne Division and commander of the Bastogne garrison., 280.
        - Col. Joseph H. Harper, commander of the 327th Gilder Infantry of Bastogne., 281.
          He is shown here on 14 December 1951, when he was assigned to the 4th Infantry Division.
        - Map -- The siege of Bastogne, 23 December 1944., 282.
        - One of 241 C-47s from IX Troop Carrier Command drops supplies for Bastogne one mile west of the town on 23 December., 283.
        - C-47 "Ain't Misbehavin'" after crash-landing near Bastogne., 284.
          If the occupants of the small camp at right were present during the successful crash-landing, they certainly received the surprise of their lives. Invasion strips, almost weathered away, adorn the C-47's fuselage.
        - Men of the 101st Airborne, many of them wounded, attended Christmas services even as the city is under siege., 285.
        - Christmas dinner at Bastogne for officers of the 101st Airborne. McAuliffe is seated fourth from the left., 286.
          Ned Moore, his acting chief of staff, is seated at the left corner of the table. On the lower right corner sits Joseph Harper. The 101st Fairborn's commander, Maj. Gen. Maxwell Taylor, is not present.
        - Airborne troops jump rope to keep warm on Christmas morning., 287.
        - A most welcome Christmas present falls from a group of nineteen C-47s., 288.
        - Soldiers, likely from Grenadier-Regiment 77, lie dead on the frozen ground where they fell on Christmas Day., 289.
        - Oberst Wolfgang Maucke, Kampfgruppe leader, 15. Panzergrenadier-Division., 290.
        - Bomb damage to Bastogne, 26 December 1944., 291.
          After Christmas, Tech/5 Krochka stayed on the job with his box camera, taking this and the next two photographs.
        - In a civilian cemetery the day after Christmas, members of the 101st Airborne Division bury their dead., 292.
        - Two 101st Airborne members drag a parapack of badly needed medical supplies through the snow near Bastogne., 293.
        - Two hapless Belgian civilians totter past a burned-out 10th Armored Division half-track near Bastogne on 27 December., 294.
          Combined with the frigid, ice-covered terrain, carcasses of destroyed vehicles convey an air of forlorn desolation in the perimeter surrounding Bastogne.
        - Maj. Gen. Hugh J. Gaffey (right), commanding general, 4th Armored Division., 295.
          This photo was taken after the war on 18 May 1945 in Neustadt, Germany. Major General Cota (left) of the 28th Infantry Division seems unimpressed by Gaffney, who by that time commanded the XXIII Corps. Perhaps he was bored by the mundane discussion that centered on the transfer of local German government functions to local units.
        - Map -- The relief of Bastogne, 26 December 1944., 296.
        - Tanks and vehicles of the 4th Armored Division advance toward Bastogne during the breakthrough., 297.
          Men line the ditch at right, keeping watch over the convoys' flank.
        - Clad in snowsuits, armored infantrymen cross a broad, snow-covered plain on 27 December, pressing ever closer to the Bastogne garrison., 298.
        - Clattering past a column of POWs, an M3 half-track from the 4th Armored Division races toward Bastogne., 299.
          The M3 mounts a water-cooled .30-caliber Browning machine gun.
        - Signal Corps photographer Pfc. D. R. Ornitz takes several well-composed, if grisly, photographs of American dead near Chaumont, Luxembourg, as Bastogne-bound half-tracks of the 4th Armored Division clatter toward their objective., 300.
          Though taken from slightly different angles and locations, these photographs together provide a wide-angle view of the road.
        - Ornitz crosses the road, looks back, and takes a picture of another American corpse as an M3 rolls toward Bastogne., 301.
          The jeep at left center was likely disabled in the Battle of Chaumont, the same action that felled the Americans nearby.
        - With Bastogne relieved, vehicles from the 4th Armored Division sit parked in its main square on 28 December., 302.
        - Lieutenant General Patton chats with Brigadier General McAuliffe after awarding him the Distinguished Service Cross on 28 December., 303.
          To their left is Lt. Col. Steve Chapuis, hero of the battle of Champs east of Bastogne. He, too, would soon receive the Distinguished Service Cross.
        - Troops of the 101st Airborne march out of Bastogne on 29 December to do battle with the Germans somewhere on the city's perimeter., 304.
        - On 30 December, a 4th Armored Division tank retriever prepares to haul out a Sherman tank disabled by German shells outside Bastogne., 305.
        - Burned-out buildings surround the debris-strewn main square in Bastogne on 30 December., 306.
          American MPs erected a new sign warning against leaving vehicles unattended. Note the disabled M3 half-track at left.
        - Bombed-out citizens of Bastogne huddle together in a horse-drawn wagon, which likely also carries most of their possessions., 307.
        - Guards of the 502d Parachute Infantry Regiment turn back civilians attempting to exit the Bastogne pocket northwest of the city on 30 December., 308.
        - Tanks and armored infantry of the 6th Armored Division attack German troops north of Bastogne on 31 December., 309.
        - Alongside members of the 101st Airborne, soldiers of the 777th AAA Battalion, which was attached to the 6th Armored Division, struggle to keep warm beside a fire on the outskirts of Bastogne on 31 December., 310.
          An M3 half-track is behind them.
        - Combat engineers from the 26th Armored Engineer Battalion, 6th Armored Division, began the task of clearing rubble from Bastogne's debris-choked streets on 1 January., 311.
        - On New Year's Day, Cpl. Martin Konopka and Pvt. Charles Kelly of the 489th AAA Battalion, 4th Armored, display a wild boar as proof that they could hit their mark, albeit on a ground target., 312.
          But it was the mayor's shotgun that made the kill.
        - A Defunct convoy of derelict gasoline trucks litters the roadside on one approach to Bastogne., 313.
      - Published Images, 1944 - 1960s (Box Photo 9, Folder 1-3)
        - On 23 December 1944 in Manhay for the first time since the opening of the German offensive, troops of the 3d Armored Division see the contrails of Allied aircraft., 314.
        - An A-20 Havoc of the 115th Photo Reconnaissance Squadron used flash and flares to take this aerial photo showing a convoy of German vehicles north of Houffalize, Belgium, on the night of 26 December., 315.
        - Ninth Air Force mechanics work on a P-38 fighter at a base in Belgium., 316.
          The two men at right are rigging pipes from a heater to warm up the P-38's right engine.
        - Bearing cheery holiday greetings for the führer, bombs await clear weather for delivery in time for Christmas., 317.
        - P-47 Thunderbolts of the 365th Fighter Group at a Ninth Air Force base in Belgium warm up and await takeoff for missions against German armored columns., 318.
          Two aircraft are taking off in the distance.
        - One more FW-190 and Luftwaffe pilot would not be available for the final defense of the Fatherland., 319.
          Maj. James Dalglish of the 354th Fighter Group scores over the Bulge.